Susanth Guru

Senior Big Data Developer

Kumbakonam, TamilNadu, India

J +91 9500980912

susanth.guru.29@gmail.com III linkedin.com/in/susanth-guru

github.com/susanth-g

About

Having **4 years** of experience in documenting, designing and implementing solutions for problems of multiple usecases by analysing technologies that fit. I also have hands on experience with multiple technologies like Hadoop, HIVE, Hbase, Spark, Cloudera, GCP and Kafka to complete data ingestion pipe lines and provision of ingested data to the product user interface.

Work Experience

CanGo Networks Pvt Ltd

Nov 2019 - Present

Chennai, TamilNadu

Senior Big Data Developer

- Designed and implemented solutions based on core JAVA for CoreServices and SpringBoot for APIs.
- Developed spark based and multithreaded performant oriented applications based on JAVA to collect and parse data from various data sources such as FTP, Command output from SSH Session, messaging queues like Kafka and Pubsub.

National Payments Corporation of India

Jul 2017 - Nov 2019

Associate Enterprise Architect

Chennai, TamilNadu

- Designed and implemented solutions based on HIVE and HBASE, Apache NIFI and Apache Phoenix.
- Developed utility jars to help operations team for scheduled daily reports which reduced the effort and time to generate reports manually everyday.

Technical Skills

Languages and Scripts: Java 8, Spring Boot, SQL, Arango QL, Shell Script, Docker YAML (basic), Python (Only to script)

DataBase Technologies(SQL): MySQL, Postgres, HIVE, Impala

DataBase Technologies(NoSQL): HBase, ArangoDB, Elastic Search

Cloud Technologies: GCP [BigQuery, PubSub, CloudStorage, CloudSQL, DataProc, Kubernetes], AWS [S3 Bucket]

Big Data Technologies: Hadoop, Apache Spark, Apache NIFI, Spark SQL, Cloudera

Developer Tools: VS Code, Eclipse, SublimeText 4, NP++, StarUML, draw.io

Terminal Tools: bash, tmux, less, vim, htop, top

Other Technologies/Frameworks: Linux, Git, SVN, JUnit, Microservices, Rserve, REST API, Kubernetes, Docker, RASA ChatBot

Projects

NIMS - Network Inventory Management System | Core JAVA, JAVA Future, Jsch Library, ArangoDB

Role: Lead and Developer

- Lead a small team of UI and API developers.
- Designed and Implemented the complete Data collection service using core JAVA to fetch and parse data from more than 24000 devices using SSH protocol for different vendors on daily basis.

MAXIS - OptiGo Al Product | JAVA Spark, Hive, Impala, MySQL, SpringBoot

Role: Developer

- Implemented a Data parser to populate performance data from csv or xml files using Spark SQL into Hive database by applying pivots and transformations over dataframes as required. Optimised Spark SQL performance with persistence.
- Designed and implemented a KQI calculator using spark SQL to re-aggregate performance data based on configurations to calculate KQI and push to Hive tables in a scheduled time interval.
- Developed CRUD API using SpringBoot to configure KQI from UI.
- Worked closely with Datascience team to invoke R code from JAVA Spring Boot with RServe.

Transaction Enquiry System - NPCI UPI, NACH | Java HTTP Servlet, Apache NIFI, Hbase, Sqoop

Role: Developer

- Designed and implemented a data ingestion pipeline using sqoop to fetch daily data from postgres and populate into Hive. Then using Apache NIFI to fetch transaction data and form rowkey based on the data, then push to Hbase.
- Implemented APIs using JAVA HTTP Servlet to fetch data from Hbase using Apache Phoenix JDBC connection.
- Developed a scheduled report generation JAR to generate reports which reduced the time to generate manual reports but enabled operations to verify or analyse the data.

RASA ChatBot - NPCI UPI, NACH | RASA Stack, Javscript, HTML, CSS

Role: Developer

- Developed a question and answer bot by training the bot with predefined NLU based intent and responses along with forms to get dynamic data by requesting an API.
- Developed to answer FAQs and transaction enquiry with transaction ID of UPI.

Publication

Emulation of IoT Gateway

Jan 2017

Emulation of IoT gateway for connecting sensor nodes in heterogenous networks within lab environments. ICCCSP - Research Gate

Education

SSN, Anna university Affil.

Master of Engineering (M.E.,) in Computer Science

JJCET, Anna university Affil.

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.,) in Computer Science

Jun 2015 – Jun 2017

Chennai, TamilNadu

Jun 2011 - May 2015

Trichy, TamilNadu

Languages

Tamil - Native, English - Fluent